You mentioned that the sense of I am
is real as such
in one of the past talks.
But simply a mistaken identity.
If I got that right.
But when I try to find this real sense
of I am to properly identify it,
I only find shifting feelings, thoughts,
and perceptions
leaving me confused about what exactly
is real about my identity if I can't
locate it anywhere. So, So,
um
I guess the answer to that is just on
the same level.
What is real about your eyes?
What is real about your ears?
What is real about your sense organs?
Because none of them can experience
itself.
Yet, there is sight. There is sound.
There is smell.
There is tactile. So,
So,
the expectation that real things are
only the ones that I can make into sense
objects, well, that's one of the deeply
rooted wrong views.
Because
what is that question even referring to
then?
Like the whoever asked that obviously is
referring to their sense of self that
they have some recognition of it.
Sure, they want it to be more. They want
to they want to make it more palpable.
That's the wrong views expectations. I
want to measure it. They want to examine
it as a sense object. But the fact is
that they were looking for something
means there was some perception of the
sense of sense of self sense of I am.
Because otherwise like the entire
question and the words and terminology
used would be completely unintelligible
if you don't even know what it refers
to. But they obviously have some sense
of I am.
Otherwise, what do they know what
they're trying to find?
And that's the point. Instead of being
preoccupied in trying to find it,
recognize the sense is already there
peripherally. As something that can never be directly
As something that can never be directly
examined, yet it always exists in the
background. So just like the eye, just like the eye,
So just like the eye, just like the eye,
just like the ears.
Because people get confused because you
can touch your eye and you think that's
the eye that sees, but it's not.
The internal sense base,
the eye that cannot see itself,
is inaccessible to you.
No matter how much you touch it, how
much you look at the picture of it, how
much you stare in the mirror.
What you're seeing is the sight,
not the thing because of which the sight
is there.
That's why when the Buddha described the
internal senses through that simile,
it's like the empty villages.
They get raided.
Defined by basically that which they're
not.
So it's the same with the sense of self.
>> [snorts]
>> Instead of following the natural
expectation of finding it as a palpable,
measurable thing, object of your senses,
of or of your thought,
put that tendency aside, don't follow
it, and instead ask yourself,
but what am I even trying to find?
That that vague sense. Like I obviously
have some recognition of its vagueness,
otherwise I wouldn't, as I said, I wouldn't even
I wouldn't, as I said, I wouldn't even
set off searching for it.
Cuz you're not just
searching for an abstract idea that you
don't understand what it refers to.
Because if you were, then why are you
even looking for it? Say if it's an
abstract idea, you hear about sense of
self, you have absolutely no idea what
the sense of I am means. You have no
reference, like it doesn't exist for
you. Why would you be looking for it on the
Why would you be looking for it on the
level of the sense objects?
Why would you be questioning its
realness because it doesn't appear as
much as means you already kind of know
that it's always there at the
background. It's felt ambiguous, not as
palpable, but you want it to be more so cuz cuz
but you want it to be more so cuz cuz
again, that's what you deem as real,
that's what you deem as as as um as
necessary. But that's why you'll never get it that
But that's why you'll never get it that
way.
It's like that, you know, the old simile
I used to give like when you look at the
stars at the night,
and if you pick a bright star and stare
at it, don't let your eyes look
elsewhere, it's like a thousands of of peripheral
it's like a thousands of of peripheral
little stars will appear. But if you try
to look at any of them, you just see
blackness. Cuz they can only be seen with
Cuz they can only be seen with
peripheral vision.
But if you don't accept that and you
keep staring, you're just going to meet
more and more frustration because again,
>> So then one could come up with a view
that well, then the sense of self
doesn't exist because I cannot
directly find it.
>> So what is it that doesn't exist then?
What are you referring to if it doesn't
exist? If it truly doesn't exist, what
are you referring to as non-existent?
>> The thing that you are denying.
>> You could more accurately say it doesn't
exist as much
as much to the layers, to the levels to
the extent that I deem existence to be,
but the fact that I can think it
the fact that I can think it
peripherally, the fact that I can deny
it means that has to be there.
Something has to be there.
>> So what can we say that something is?
>> Well, again, you fall back into same
question. What could I say that that
something is means how could I make that
something to be more than it is because
I don't like the ambiguity of it and my
mind is not used to seeing it as such. I
need to make it more palpable.
So, any question what is it? Is it? Is
it not? Is it both? Is it not?
Revolves around, come on, make it more
than it is so that I can deal with it.
That's why the Buddha wouldn't answer
those questions.
Cuz you're just reinforcing the the very
kind of
wrong view in the very wrong way of
going about it. So, that
So, that
not quite as real
sense of self is real as such
to that extent.
So, instead of trying to interfere or
change or modify the extent, you need to
learn how to see it
impartially.
>> And so, that is a you said that that is
a
sense of self.
The owner
is uh
a product or a symptom of this
assumption of ownership.
>> Yes, theoretically speaking, but
practically that knowledge is
irrelevant. It's just going to serve as
an excuse and explanation of what my
sense of self is, which is again done
for the sake of making it more
definable. >> [snorts]
>> [snorts]
>> Sense of self is there.
Ownership is there. Cannot be accessed
directly.
It's always in the background. It's
always peripheral.
And it's a symptom of the problem.
>> Symptom of the problem.
>> Yeah.
It's like
the heat is there because there is
obviously fire and the fire is there
because the fuel is constantly provided
for it.
So, if you try to get rid of the heat
while still feeding the fire, well, it's
a very futile endeavor.
And that's pretty much what people are
doing. They they'll I try to deal with
heat. I with the sense of self. I try to
do this. I do this. Anatta.
Repeat Anatta mantras and deny it and
say it's not real and sciences explain
that everything is constantly changing.
While still inadvertently and ignorantly
continuing the field to fuel the very
fuel the very fire because of which the heat
the very fire because of which the heat
it's still going to be there. No matter
how much you deny it as as an
afterthought, it's still going to be
felt. It's still going to burn.
It's still going to burn.
>> [snorts]
>> So Yeah, you recognize Yeah, this heat
is a bit too hot. It's burning.
It's too much. It's a problem.
So how do I get rid of it? Well
by extinguishing the underneath the
underlying fire.
So what is that underlying fire? Actions
rooted in greed, aversion, distraction,
ignorance, resistance, hindrances,
denial, unbeneficial basically acts by body,
unbeneficial basically acts by body,
speech, and mind.
That is the fire. That is the fuel for
the fire.
>> [snorts]
>> That's also why
you have to train in it to see it
and to get benefit from it.
Because just providing an answer
will not immediately extinguish the
fire. Or even just like
not providing the fuel for a day or two
will not immediately show you that the
fire is lessening. Why? Well, because it
was overloaded with fuel before that.
So there is a bit of a delay
that you have to as I say endure
until you recognize that the fire is
lessening and the heat is diminishing.
>> Or the fire is out and then the fire is
out. >> Eventually it will be out, of course.
>> But you can't you can get a view that
the fire can go out.
And the heat will go out.
>> Yeah. And that's why I say the sense of
self is real as such. Ambiguous,
peripheral, not directly accessible, but
it is real as such.
because the heat is real as such.
Not seeing the heat as an indirect
by-product of an underlying problem
will exactly make you go about it the
way people go about it. Try to make the
sense of self into something measurable,
something deniable, something that's not
real, something that's an illusion. In
other words, just denying the heat
because you can't find a fire.
And then just trying to cope by saying,
"Well, you know, it's not real anyway."
What is it anyway when I can't
Cuz you can't. Can you touch the heat?
Can you see the heat?
No. Yet, it's there.
Yet, it's there.
Felt. Burning. Pressuring.
The feeling is palpable.
>> You can, you know,
>> Yes, if you make
the right associations.
It's not going to be seen on its own.
You're not going to make the connection
seemingly random acts
of desire, irritation, and stuff, and
then subsequent heat that pressures you
in regard to completely different
things. So, that's why the learning is
So, that's why the learning is
necessary. So, you start to look for the
right connections.
And putting two and two together.
>> [snorts]
>> And initially, yeah, you might even have
to take it on faith
that certain acts are increasing the
heat, but you don't see the connection.
Well, you have nothing to lose if you take it
you have nothing to lose if you take it
on faith
because the actions that are required
from you to cultivate are beneficial
even in the worldly sense.
Don't follow the desires blindly. Don't
act out of anger.
By body, speech, and mind. Don't
entertain such thoughts. Like, well,
that's a good thing anyway, isn't it?
Everybody values that, even people have
no interest in Dhamma.
If you ask them, "Is anger bad?" They're
like, "Yeah." This is How is anger felt?
Pleasantly or unpleasantly? Well, it's
unpleasant.
How is desire felt?
And if you can't get what you want, but
desire remains there highlighted, oh,
it's unpleasant.
So, it would be good if if it weren't
there. It would be good if you would be
in a bit more control in regards to
things. Yeah, it would be nice. It would
be
It would be peaceful, wouldn't it? The
mind would be quieted. The mind would be
more content.
So, you have nothing to lose even if you
take it on faith
that those kind of behaviors and not
following those types of other
unbeneficial behaviors is good.
Plus, as the Buddha said in the his
instructions, it's
as a result of those things, the heat
will lessen.
As a result of those things, your own
kind of need and compulsion for things
to be clearly palpable, more defined, to
be real, that will diminish as well. You
recognize it Oh, look at that thing.
It's not as real that is real as such.
Oh, look at that thing. It's not I can't
put my finger on it. It is real as such.
The nature of un-being unable to put a
finger on something is real as such.
Ambiguity. Uncertainty. Real as such. And you don't
Uncertainty. Real as such. And you don't
need to change it in order to deal with
it. You see it for what it is.
You see it for what it is.
That's how you go over doubt as well.
Overcome the doubt.
The uncertainty.
You overcome the doubt by recognizing
uncertainty real as such.
And not feeling justified in
automatically trying to get rid of it or
explaining it away.
>> [snorts]